上一节我们讨论了CBC-MAC和NMAC
In the last segment we talked about the
CBC-MAC and the NMAC, but throughout
当时我们总是假设信息长度是分组长度的倍数
the segment we always assumed that the
message length was a multiple of the block
本节，我们将看到当信息长度不是分组长度的整数倍时
size. In this segment, we're going to see
what to do when the message length is not
该怎么办。记得加密CBC-MAC，或简写为ECBC-MAC
a multiple of the block size. So recall
that the encrypted CBC mac or ECBC-MAC for
使用了伪随机置换F来计算CBC函数
short uses pseudorandom permutation F to
actually compute the CBC function as we
这是我们上节讨论的。但在上节里，我们总是假设
discussed in the last segment. But in the
last segment, we always assumed that the
信息本身可以被分解成整数个分组密码的分组
message itself could be broken into an
integer number of blocks for the block
问题是当信息长度不是分组长度的整数倍时
cipher. And the question is what to do
when the message length is not a multiple
该怎么办。这里我们有一个信息，它的最后一个分组
of the block size. So here we have a
message where the last block actually is
比满分组要短，问题是如何计算这种情况的ECBC-MAC
shorter than the full block and the
question is how to compute the ECBC-MAC in
答案当然是补齐信息。第一个想到的补齐信息的方法
that case. So the solution of course is to
pad the message and the first pad that
是简单地在信息后面补0。换句话说
comes to mind is to simply pad the message
with all zeros. In other words we take the
我们取最后一个分组，在后面补0直到其长度
和一个满分组的长度一样
last block and just add zeros to it until
the last block becomes as long as one full
我给大家的问题是，这个MAC是否安全？
block size. And so my question to you is
whether the resulting MAC is secure. So
答案是否定的，这个MAC不安全。我来解释为什么
the answer is no, the MAC is not secure.
And let me explain why, basically the
问题在于这样就可以算出新的信息m
problem is that it's possible now to come
up with messages so that message m and the
信息m联结上0，正好也有同样的补齐
message m concatenated zero happen to have
exactly the same pad. And as a result once
一旦我们带入m和m||0到ECBC中，我们会得到同样的标签输出
we plug in both m and m||0 into ECBC we'll
get the same tag out, which means that
这意味着m和m||0有着同样的标签
both m and m||0 have the
same tag and therefore the attacker can
因此攻击者可以实施存在性伪造。他会问信息m的标签
mount an existential forgery. He would ask
for the tag on the message m. And then he
然后他会输出伪造的标签和信息m||0
would output as its forgery the tag and the
message m||0. And it's
容易看出为什么会这样。更清楚地
easy to say why that's the case. Basically, to be absolutely clear here, we have our
我们有信息m，补齐后成为m000。我们必须加三个0
message m, which after padding becomes m000. So we had to add three
这里我们有信息m0，m且以0结尾
0's to it. And here we have the message m
zero, an m that ends with zero. And after
补齐后，我们现在必须再加两个0。大家看
padding, we basically now have to add two
0's to it. And lo and behold, they become
它们成为了相同的补齐，它们的补齐严格相同
the same pad, so that they're gonna have
exactly the same tag which allows the
这就让攻击者得以实施存在性攻击。因此这不是个好想法
adversary to mount the existential forgery
attack. So this is not a good idea. In
事实上全部补0是个糟糕的点子。想一想具体情况
fact appending all 0s is a terrible idea.
And if you think about concrete case where
就会有问题。想想自动打扫房间系统
this comes up. Imagine the automatic
clearing house system used for clearing
用于处理支票的。我可能有一张100美元的支票，
支票上有标签。现在
checks. I might have a check for a $100
and the tag on that check. Well, now, the
攻击者可以在我的支票后面加个0，变成1000美元了
attacker basically could append a zero to
my check and make it a check for $1000,
这不会改变标签。这就可以扩展信息
and that wouldn't actually change the tag.
So this ability to extend the message
不用改变标签，将会造成灾难性的后果
without changing the tag actually could
have pretty disastrous consequences. So I
所以我希望这个例子能说服大家，
补齐函数本身必须是一一映射的函数
hope this example convinces you that the
padding function itself must be a one to
换句话说，它应当是将两个不同的信息映射到
one function. In other words, it should be
the case that two distinct messages always
不同的两个补齐的信息。我们不应在补齐函数上有碰撞
map to two distinct padded messages. We
shouldn't actually have a collision on the
或者说，补齐函数必须是可逆的
padding function. Another way of saying it
is that the padding function must be
这保证了补齐函数是一一映射的
invertible. That guarantees that the
padding function is one to one. So a
实现的标准方法是由国际标准化组织ISO提出的
standard way to do this was proposed by
the International Standards Organization
他们提议，我们把字符串100000附在信息后面
ISO. What they suggested is basically,
let's append the string 100000 to the end
使得信息长度是分组长度的倍数
of the message to make the message be a
multiple of the block length. Now to see
看得出这个补齐是可逆的，我们只需描述求逆的算法
that this padding is invertible, all we do
is describe the inversion algorithm
就是简单地从右往左地扫描信息
which simply is gonna scan the message
from right to left, until it hits the
直到遇见第一个1，然后移除所有在1右边的位
first one and then it's gonna remove all
the bits to the right of this one,
包括1本身。大家看到，一旦我们照着这样移除
including the one. And you see that once
we've removed the pattern this way, we
我们就可以获得原来的信息。那么这是一个例子
obtain the original message. So here's an
example, so here we have a message where
这里，我们信息的最后一个分组正好比满分组短
the last block happens to be shorter than
the block length, and then we
然后我们把字符串100附在后面。容易看出如何补齐
append the 1,0,0 string to it.
It's very easy to see what the pad is,
从右边看，容易找到第一个1，我们可以移除这些补齐
simply look for the first one from the
right, we can remove this pad and recover
恢复原信息。现在有一个特殊情况，也是挺重要的
the original message back. Now there's one
corner case that's actually quite
那就是如果原信息长度已经是
important, and that is what do we do if
the original message length is already the
分组长度的倍数了呢？在这种情况下
multiple of a block size? In that case
it's really very, very important that we
加一个假的分组将是非常重要。包含补齐1000
add an extra dummy block. That contains
the pad 1000. And again, I can't tell you
我都不知道有多少产品和标准犯过这个错误
how many products and standards have
actually made this mistake where they
它们没有加假的分组，导致MAC是不安全的
didn't add a dummy block and as a result,
the MAC is insecure because there's an
因为存在一个简单的存在性伪造。我来告诉大家为什么
easy existential forgery attack. And let
me show you why. So suppose in case the
假设在这种情况下，信息长度是分组长度的倍数
假设我们不加假的分组
message is a multiple of a block length,
suppose we didn't add a dummy block and we
我们计算这个信息的MAC，结果是。。
literally MAC-ed this message here. Well,
the result now is that if you look at
如果你看这个信息的长度是分组长度的倍数
the message which is a multiple of the
block size and a message which is not a
还有一个信息的长度不是分组长度的倍数，
但它被补齐到分组大小了
multiple of the block size but is padded
to the block size, and imagine it so
想像一下，这个信息m'以100结尾
happens that this message m prime one
happens to end with 1-0-0. At this point,
这里大家发现，这个原信息。我这样画
you realize that here, the original
message. Here, let me draw it this way.
大家发现原信息在补齐之后
You realize that the original message
after padding would become identical to
与第二个根本没补齐的信息是一样的
the second message that was not padded at
all. And as a result, if I ask for the tag
因此，如果我问这个信息的标签，我也获得了
第二个以100结尾的信息的标签
on this message over here, I would obtain
also the tag on the second message that
好，如果我们不加假的分组
happened to end in 1-0-0. Okay, so if we
didn't add the dummy block, basically,
补齐将不是可逆的，因为两个不同的信息
again, the pad would be not invertible,
because two different messages, two
正好被映射到了同样的补齐结果
distinct messages, happen to map to the
same padded result. Again, as a result,
因此MAC将不安全了。总结一下，这个ISO标准
是完美的补齐方法
the MAC becomes insecure. So to summarize,
this ISO standard is a perfectly fine way
但大家要记住也要加假的分组
to pad, except you have to remember also
to add a dummy block in case message is a
当信息长度是分组长度的倍数时。现在也许有人想知道
multiple of the block length to begin
with. Now some of you might be wondering
是否有一种补齐方式，从不需要加假的分组
if there is a padding scheme that never
needs to add a dummy block, and the answer
答案是，如果你看确定的补齐函数
is that if you look at a deterministic
padding function, then it's pretty easy to
容易证明所有情况下我们都需要补齐
argue that there will always be cases
where we need to pad, and the reason is
原因是长度为分组倍数的信息数目
just literally the number of messages that
are multiples of the block length is much
比长度不必是分组倍数的信息数目少得多
smaller than the total number of messages
that need not be a multiple of the block
(事实上，数目比约1:2)
因此我们无法获得一个从大的所有信息的集合
length. And as a result we can't have a
one to one function from this bigger
到小的分组倍数长的信息集合的一一映射
set of all messages to the smaller set of
messages which are a multiple of
总会有我们必须扩展原信息的情况
the block length. There will always be cases
where we have to extend the original
这种情况就对应于加假的补齐分组
message and in this case that would
correspond to adding this dummy padding
但是，有一个非常聪明的方法叫做CMAC
block. However, there is a very clever
idea called CMAC which shows that using a
可以使用一个随机的补齐函数，不用加假分组了
randomized padding function we can avoid
having to ever add a dummy block. And so
我来解释下CMAC如何工作。CMAC使用三个密钥
let me explain how CMAC works. So CMAC
actually uses three keys. And, in fact,
事实上，这叫做三密钥机制。第一个密钥K
sometimes this is called a three key
construction. So this first key, K, is
用于CBC计算，标准的CBC-MAC算法。然后密钥K1和K2
used in the CBC, the standard CBC MAC
algorithm. And then the keys, K1 and K2,
仅用于最后一个分组的补齐
are used just for the padding scheme at
the very, very last block. And in fact in
事实上在CMAC标准中，密钥K1和K2是由密钥K推出的
the CMAC standard, the keys K1, K2 are
derived from the key K by some sort of a
使用某种伪随机数发生器。CMAC如下工作
pseudo random generator. So the way CMAC
works is as follows. Well, if the message
如果信息长度正好是分组长度的整数倍，那么
我们采用ISO补齐的方法
happens to not be a multiple of a block
length, then we append the ISO padding to
但我们还要把这最后一个分组和密钥K1异或
it. But then we also XOR this last
block with a secret key, K1, that the
攻击者不知道K1。但是如果信息长度是分组长度的倍数
adversary doesn't know. However, if the
message is a multiple of the block length,
那么当然，我们不做扩展，而是与另一密钥K2异或
then of course, we don't append anything
to it. But we XOR it with a different
攻击者也不知道K2
key, K2, that, again, the adversary
doesn't actually know. So it turns out,
这样做的话，不可能实施对级联函数、原CBC
所适用的扩展攻击
just by doing that, it's now impossible to
apply the extension attacks that we could
因为可怜的攻击者
do on the cascade function, and on
raw CBC. Because the poor
不知道最后分组运行了哪个函数
adversary actually doesn't know what is
the last block that went into the
他不知道K1，因此他不知道这个点的值
function. He doesn't know K1, and therefore,
he doesn't know the value at this
所以他无法实施扩展攻击。事实上
particular point and as a result, he can't do
an extension attack. In fact, this is a
这个命题可以证明。这个机制就是简单地
provable statement. And so that this
construction here is simply by XOR-ing
异或K1或是异或K2，是个PRF
尽管不需要做原CBC函数后面的
K1 or XOR-ing K2 is really a PRF.
Despite not having to do a final
最终加密步骤。那么这是一个好处
encryption step after the raw CBC
function is computed. So, that's one
没有最后的加密步骤。第二个好处是
benefit, that there's no final encryption
step. And the second benefit is that we resolve
我们解决了"是否发生了补齐"所带来的歧义
this ambiguity between whether padding did
happen or padding didn't happen by using
通过使用两个密钥来区分，"信息长度是分组长度的倍数
two different keys to distinguish the case
that the message is a multiple of the block
与信息长度不是分组长度的倍数，而我们补齐了"这两种情况
length versus the case where it's not but
we have a pad appended to the message. So
两个不同密钥解决了两种情况之间的歧义
the two distinct keys resolve this
ambiguity between the two cases, and as a
因此这个补齐是充分安全的。如我所说
result, this padding actually is
sufficiently secure. And as I said,
CMAC有一个漂亮的定理告诉我们
there's actually a nice security theorem
that goes with CMAC that shows that the
CMAC机制是一个伪随机函数，具有与
CMAC construction really is a pseudo-random
function, with the same security
CBC-MAC同样的安全性。那么我想提一下
properties as CBC-MAC. So I wanted to
mention that CMAC is a federal standard
CMAC是NIST标准化的联邦标准，如果大家最近想用CBC-MAC
standardized by NIST and if you now, these
days, wanted to use a CBC-MAC for
还是去用CMAC吧，作为标准方法
anything, you would actually be using CMAC
as the standard way to do it. But
特别是在CMAC中，底层函数是AES
particularly in CMAC, the underlying block
cypher is AES and that gives us a secure
可以给我们一个由AES推出的安全的CBC-MAC。
本节完结，下节我们讨论
CBC-MAC derived from AES. So that's the end
on the segment and in the next segment
一种并行的MAC机制
we'll talk about a parallel MAC.